Email: aidan.boland@ucd.ie Web: http://www.aboland.ie

Personal Profile

Self motivated with broad ranging practical work experience in demanding environments. Outgoing, energetic and committed with well-developed communication skills, able to liaise effectively with people at all levels, an enthusiastic team player and equally effective working independently.

Employment

2016 - Present Lecturer, University College Dublin, Belfield, Dublin 4.

Lecturing an online undergraduate module in the School of Mathematics and Statistics titled 'Practical Statistics'.

This involves creating and delivering lectures, creating and grading assignments and exams, and co-ordinating tutors for computer labs in Minitab and R.

2015 - Present Postdoctoral Researcher, University College Dublin, Belfield, Dublin 4.

& Clavis Insight, D'Olier St., Dublin 2.

Researching text classification methods for use in e-commerce analytics.

This project involves research into both supervised and unsupervised text classification methods with the aim of solving an industry specific problem.

2010 - 2015 Tutor, University College Dublin, Belfield, Dublin 4.

Tutored undergraduate and postgraduate students over a broad range of courses including probability theory, actuarial statistics, Bayesian analysis, data programming and multivariate analysis.

Demonstrated and tutored computer practical classes (SAS, R and Minitab) of up to fifty students for both undergraduates and postgraduates.

Graded undergraduate and postgraduate assignments in addition to final examinations.

Created screencasts and administerd discussion boards for an online module: 'Data programming with R'.

Summer 2012 Statistical Consultant, AOL, Heuston South Quarter, Dublin 8.

Undertook a three month study to create an algorithm to autmotically detect spam searches on AOL's search engine.

Summer 2011 Statistical Consultant, CSTAR, University College Dublin, Belfield, Dublin 4.

Carried out consultations and analysis for health sciences researchers.

2008 - 2010 I.T. Technician, Surfbox (Ormonde Technologies) Thomastown, Kilkenny.

Maintained and installed Coin and Credit Card operated Internet terminals throughout Ireland. Constructed new terminals also.

2004 - 2011 Course Marshall/Starter, Kilkenny Golf Club, Kilkenny.

Managed club competitions and course play at weekends and during holidays. Also liaised and facilitated golf society outings.

Education

2011 - 2015 PhD. in Statistics

University College Dublin, Belfield, Dublin 4.

Title: 'Overcoming Intractable Likelihoods' (Supervisor: Prof. Nial Friel).

2010 - 2011 M.Sc. in Statistics (First Class Honours)

University College Dublin, Belfield, Dublin 4.

Minor thesis: 'Supervised Probabilistic Classification' (Supervisor: Prof. Nial Friel).

<u>Courses covered:</u> Multivariate Analysis, Mathematical Statistics, Bayesian Analysis, Time Series Analysis, Applied Statistical Modelling, Data Programming, Monte Carlo Inference and Stochastic Models.

2006 - 2010 B.Sc. Degree in Mathematical Science (Upper Second Class Honours)
University College Dublin, Belfield, Dublin 4.

Courses included:

Statistics - Probability Distributions, Statistical Inference I, Biostatistics,
Statistical Inference II, Survey Sampling, Linear Models I,
Statistics & Visualization, Linear Models II, Data Analysis I,
Actuarial Statistics I, Nonparametric Statistics, Design of Experiments,
Survival Analysis, Categorical Data Analysis,
Data Analysis II and Linear Models with Complex Structures.

Mathematics - Discrete Mathematics, Financial Mathematics,
Vector Spaces and Coding, Calculus of Several Variables,
Introduction to Analysis, Polynomial Rings/Group Theory,
Functions of One Complex Variable, Differential Geometry
and Advanced Linear Algebra.

Mathematical Physics - Analytical & Quantum Mechanics, Vector Calculus,
Introduction to Fluids & Waves,
Partial Differential Equations
and Dynamical Systems.

Skills Acquired

Networking, presenting, report writing and interpersonal skills: Developed through attending and presenting at conferences and workshops, writing my masters and PhD theses, and preparing papers for publication.

<u>Teamwork and communication skills:</u> Developed through participation in group projects during my undergraduate degree and also through playing rugby.

Computer skills: Extensive knowledge of Microsoft Word, Excel, PowerPoint and IATEX. Programming in several statistical (computing) languages - R and Minitab, programming in C and C++. Working knowledge in Python, SAS, SPSS and Genstat.

<u>Self-motivation and excellent work ethic:</u> Working independently to overcome problems, manage large workload and plan nature of work.

Interests and activities:

I enjoy all kinds of sport. I am particularly interested in rugby and currently play with Bective Rangers Football Club. I have also played at school level and represented my school in a Leinster Development Cup final. In addition, I enjoy playing golf and have represented Kilkenny Golf Club at Junior Level for which I hold two Leinster medals. Further interests include soccer, watersports and socialising with friends.